<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The: iiii: leues of the trueloue</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1510</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05208</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15345</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109370</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845020</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845020</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9890</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05208)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9890)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 71:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The: iiii: leues of the trueloue</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Flete strete at the sygne of the sonne, by wynkyn de worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Enprented at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1510?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and address from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9890:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9890:1"/>
            <p>The .iiii. leues of the trueloue</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut</figDesc>
                  <p>Holde this a token <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>for your ſake</l>
                     <l>I ſhall it take</l>
                  </lg>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="alliterative_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:9890:2"/>
            <lg n="1">
               <l>IN a mornyng of may wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> medowes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge.</l>
               <l>Braunches and bloſſomes of bryght colours</l>
               <l>As I wente by a well on my playenge</l>
               <l>Thorowe a mery orcharde ſayenge myn oures</l>
               <l>Where byrdes full byſely began for to ſynge</l>
               <l>The bowes to borge on borde to the browes</l>
               <l>I was ware of a may that made mornynge</l>
               <l>She ſate and ſyghed amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the fayre floures</l>
               <l>ſo ſwete</l>
               <l>¶ She made mournynge ynoughe</l>
               <l>Her wepynge dyd my herte woo</l>
               <l>To a derne I me droughe</l>
               <l>Her wyll for to knowe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <l>¶ Stylly I ſtalked and ſtode in that ſtede</l>
               <l>To wytte of her wyll and of her wylde thought</l>
               <l>Then caſt ſhe her kercheffes the calle of hede</l>
               <l>Wronge ſhe her handes and wrothly ſhe wrought</l>
               <l>¶ She ſayd mylde mary ryght thou my rede</l>
               <l>Of all the welthe of the worlde wolde I nought</l>
               <l>But ſende me ſome ſolaſe or ſone I ſhall be dede</l>
               <l>A ſyghte of that ſelcath I haue it longe ſought</l>
               <l>with care</l>
               <l>¶ Then ſpake the turtyll on a tree </l>
               <l>With fayre wordes and free</l>
               <l>Bryght byrde of bewte</l>
               <l>Why ſygheſt thou ſo ſore</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <l>¶ O fayre foule ſpare not thy ſpeche nor thy ſpell</l>
               <l>They kerpynge doth me comforte to herken and bere</l>
               <l>All my wyll and my thought wolde I the tell</l>
               <l>My wo and my wandrynge and thou wolde come nere</l>
               <l>¶ Then he lyghted louely with her for to dwell</l>
               <l>To comforte the comly and euer her chere</l>
               <l>She blyſſyd his body with boke and with bell</l>
               <l>And loued our lady that ſente her that fere</l>
               <l>ſo fre</l>
               <l>¶ Whan I was ſory</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:9890:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Beſought I our lady </l>
               <l>And ſhe ſente me company </l>
               <l>Bleſſyd maye ſhe be</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <l>¶ O fayre foule full of loue ſo mylde and ſwete</l>
               <l>To medle on a mater nowe we maye begynne</l>
               <l>Trueloue I haue ſought fer by waye and byſtrete</l>
               <l>In many fayre orchardes where floures be in,</l>
               <l>¶ So ferre as I haue ſoughte ſawe I none yet</l>
               <l>Full fewe I haue founde of more or ot myn</l>
               <l>Bryght byrde of ble my ſorowe myght thou bete</l>
               <l>Wolde thou me wyſſhe wyſely a trueloue to wynne</l>
               <l>with ryght</l>
               <l>¶ For when I wene ſoneſt</l>
               <l>To fynde loue beſt </l>
               <l>Then ſo feble is it feſt. </l>
               <l>And fareth all on flyght</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <l>¶ The wytte of wymen is wonder to here</l>
               <l>Is all thy ſory ſyghynge to ſeke a loue true</l>
               <l>All thy lyfe dayes may thou ſeke &amp; neuer none be nere</l>
               <l>But yf thou had counſayle of one that I knewe</l>
               <l>¶ Yf thou beſet to ſeke trueloue I ſhall the lere</l>
               <l>Where it is ſpryngynge euermore newe</l>
               <l>Without ony fautynge full fayre and full clere</l>
               <l>Or caſtynge of coloures or chaungynge of hewe</l>
               <l>full yare</l>
               <l>¶ I dare baldly ſaye </l>
               <l>Thre is no loue that laſteth aye</l>
               <l>Without treaſon or traye. </l>
               <l>But yf it begyn there</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <l>¶ Loke where thou fyndeſt growyng a truloue greſſe</l>
               <l>That with .iiij. leues fully is ſet aboute</l>
               <l>The fyrſt lefe we maye lyken to the kynge of blyſſe</l>
               <l>He that wrought all the worlde with in and without</l>
               <l>¶ He made heuen with his hande and all paradyſe</l>
               <l>And this mery mydell erthe without ony doubte</l>
               <l>All the welthe of the worlde holly is his</l>
               <l>In whome we ought to lyue &amp; lowe for to loute</l>
               <l>full wele</l>
               <l>¶ Holde we this in mynde </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:9890:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Tyll we may theſe felawes fynde</l>
               <l>The true loue and kynde. </l>
               <l>That neuermore ſhall kele</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <l>¶ The ſeconde lefe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueloue I lyken to goddes ſone</l>
               <l>That to the fyrſt lefe is felawe and fere</l>
               <l>The thyrde to the holy gooſt togyder they wone</l>
               <l>All hole in a godhede and perſones thre</l>
               <l>¶ They be rulers of water ſonne and of mone</l>
               <l>The fourth lefe of pryce without ony pere</l>
               <l>Whan the comly kynge is ſet in his trone</l>
               <l>Comly of colours and curteyſe of chere</l>
               <l>with grace</l>
               <l>¶ All this worlde he began </l>
               <l>And of wyndes and waters wan</l>
               <l>Then he marked man</l>
               <l>After his owne face</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <l>¶ Fyrſt he made Adam and than he made Eue</l>
               <l>He put them in to paradyſe in grete degre</l>
               <l>Forbyddynge nothynge to hym and his wyfe</l>
               <l>But a grene apple that dyde growe on a tre</l>
               <l>¶ Than ſory ſathanas ſought them belyfe</l>
               <l>To awake our wo curſed myght he be</l>
               <l>Then toke they the apple that ſtyred moche ſtryfe</l>
               <l>The foule fende was glad that ſyght for to ſe</l>
               <l>for tene</l>
               <l>¶ The fyrſt leue was wo </l>
               <l>Whan floures fell hym fro</l>
               <l>That his frendes ſholde to hell go</l>
               <l>For an apple grene</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <l>¶ Then began the fyrſt lefe to mourne for vs all</l>
               <l>For his holy handy werke that was forlorne</l>
               <l>Gabryell to hym he dyde call</l>
               <l>Forth came he comly and kneled hym beforne</l>
               <l>¶ He ſayd to mylde mary on meſſage thou ſhall</l>
               <l>To bere her gladde tydynges of her I wyll be borne</l>
               <l>Thus he ſent his ſone out of his hye halle</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:9890:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>To the mylde mayde on a mery morne</l>
               <l>and her gret</l>
               <l>¶ Gabryell with the fayre face</l>
               <l>Sayd mary full of grace</l>
               <l>Pyerles in euery place</l>
               <l>With myrth thou arte met</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <l>¶ Thou ſalte conceyue a chylde comly and clere</l>
               <l>All the bale of the worlde in the it ſhall be let</l>
               <l>She ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were a meruayle &amp; I a chylde ſholde bere</l>
               <l>For I was neuer maryed with no man yet</l>
               <l>¶ He ſayd beholde to thy coſyn y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyued to yere</l>
               <l>Elyzabeth in her age that longe hath ben led</l>
               <l>O lorde I am thy mayde ſayd mary ſo dere</l>
               <l>And holy in thy ſeruyce is my herte ſet</l>
               <l>full ſtyll</l>
               <l>¶ Blyſſed be the ſwete wyght</l>
               <l>That goddes ſone in lyght </l>
               <l>Become man full of myght</l>
               <l>With the faders wyll</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="11">
               <l>¶ Now is the ſeconde lefe for our loue mooſt</l>
               <l>Lyght in the lady that gabryell grete</l>
               <l>Without ony treaſon true for to tryſt</l>
               <l>With myrthe in a mayde is god and man met</l>
               <l>¶ This is the fader and the ſonne and the holy goſte</l>
               <l>Thre lefes of loue without ony lette</l>
               <l>The fourth is a mayde choſen for chaſte</l>
               <l>Suche another truloue was neuer in londe ſette</l>
               <l>for bote</l>
               <l>¶ The fourth lefe maye neuer fall </l>
               <l>But euer they ſprynge ſhall</l>
               <l>So gentely they Ioyne all</l>
               <l>On a ryche roote</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12">
               <l>¶ Now hathe the thyrde lefe a ſwete felowe taken</l>
               <l>For loue in lady is our lady lyght</l>
               <l>Ioſeph her wedded and with her dyd gone</l>
               <l>In the cyte of bethelem there buylded the bryght</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:9890:4"/>
               <l>¶ Bytwene an oxe and an awe pryde was there none</l>
               <l>A bleſſyd chylde there was borne on cryſtmas nyght</l>
               <l>There roſe a ſterre ſtabely ſhewed and ſhone</l>
               <l>Thre kynge of colayne theron hadde a ſyght</l>
               <l>and ſought</l>
               <l>¶ They offered to hym as they wolde </l>
               <l>Myrre Rykyls and golde</l>
               <l>He thanked them many folde</l>
               <l>And to blyſſe he them brought</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13">
               <l>¶ Vnhappy Herode the tydynges herde tell</l>
               <l>That a chylde was borne that kynge ſholde be</l>
               <l>He dyde make meſſagers and ſende them full ſnell</l>
               <l>To ſlee all male chyldren in that countre</l>
               <l>¶ They lefte none alyue but all dyd they kyll</l>
               <l>They ſpytted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on ſpere poyntes grete pyte was to ſe</l>
               <l>Ioſeph with his wedded wyfe wolde no longer dwell</l>
               <l>But ledde her in to Egypte with her leues thre</l>
               <l>for to ſaue</l>
               <l>¶ The chyldren coude theyr dethe take</l>
               <l>For the trueloue ſake</l>
               <l>More myrthe they dyde make</l>
               <l>For hym ſelfe wolde they haue</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14">
               <l>¶ Yet wolde our lorde do more for his frendes dere</l>
               <l>For his holy handy werkes to helle wolde he gone</l>
               <l>To gyue enſample his lawe for to lere</l>
               <l>Saynt Iohan cryſtened hym in flome iordane</l>
               <l>¶ For xxx. pens was he ſolde thorowe a falſe fere</l>
               <l>Vnto the Iewes that wolde hym haue ſlayne</l>
               <l>All he ſuffred for our ſake and hymſelfe was clere</l>
               <l>By a kyſſe was he knowen and ſone was be taken</l>
               <l>alſo</l>
               <l>¶ It was grete pyte for to ſe </l>
               <l>When he ſholde blenke of his ble</l>
               <l>The ſeconde lefe of the thre</l>
               <l>The fourth was full woo</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="15">
               <l>¶ Pylate was Iuſtyſe and ſpake vp on hye</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:9890:4"/>
               <l>For to deme Iheſu that Iudas hathe ſolde</l>
               <l>He ſayd loke lordes trouthe for to trye</l>
               <l>The ſemly is fautles ſaye what they wolde</l>
               <l>¶ The Iues on pylate began for to crye</l>
               <l>He calleth hymſelfe a kyng ſuche bourdes be to bolde</l>
               <l>Yf thou wylte not deme hym to daye for to dye</l>
               <l>Loude before the emperoure the tale ſhall be tolde</l>
               <l>for drede</l>
               <l>¶ A fury dome he gaue hym there</l>
               <l>And ſayd that he coude ſaye no more </l>
               <l>I rede ye take hym there</l>
               <l>And forthe ye hym lede</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="16">
               <l>¶ Alas for the fourthe lefe was lefte alone</l>
               <l>When her fayre felowſhyp was taken and torne</l>
               <l>Beten wich ſharpe ſcourges body and bone</l>
               <l>Syth ſpred on a croſſe and crowned with thorne</l>
               <l>¶ Thorowe his handes &amp; fete herte nayles dyd gone</l>
               <l>A bryght ſpere to his herte ſharpely was borne</l>
               <l>He ſhed his blode for our loue and lyfe leued hym none</l>
               <l>After and ayzell they gaue hym for ſcorne</l>
               <l>with gyle</l>
               <l>¶ It was grete pyte for to ſe </l>
               <l>Whan he was nayled on a tre</l>
               <l>The ſeconde lefe ſycurly</l>
               <l>Dyed for vs all</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="17">
               <l>¶ The fourthe lefe of the loke alone ſhe ſtode</l>
               <l>Wryngynge her handes and wepynge for woo</l>
               <l>With a mournynge chere and mylde mode</l>
               <l>Her ſonnes coloure faded and wexed wonder blo</l>
               <l>¶ Downe by his whyte ſydes ran the redde blode</l>
               <l>Harde roches dyd ryue and temples in two</l>
               <l>Then ſwowned the fourth lefe and to the ground yode</l>
               <l>Alas for the trueloue that it ſholde twyne ſo</l>
               <l>full yare</l>
               <l>¶ She ſawe her dere ſonne dye</l>
               <l>Saynt Iohan ſtode her by </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:9890:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> comforte the lady</l>
               <l>That was caſt in care</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="18">
               <l>¶ Yet ſpake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noble kynge that was nayled on the tre</l>
               <l>To his moder ſo mylde that was mournyng that tyde</l>
               <l>And ſayd leue thy wepyng woman mourne not for me</l>
               <l>Take Iohan too thy ſone that wonneth the beſyde</l>
               <l>¶ Iohan take mary to thy moder for to myrthe the</l>
               <l>To kepe and to comforte your blyſſe for to byde</l>
               <l>The hote blode of his ſydes cauſed longes to ſe</l>
               <l>That ſought by a ſpere ſhafte fro his wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des wyde</l>
               <l>that daye</l>
               <l>¶ It was grete pyte for to ſe </l>
               <l>Whan he was take of the tree</l>
               <l>The ſeconde lefe of the thre</l>
               <l>Was cloſed in clay</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="19">
               <l>¶ Whan he was take of the rode and delued ful yare</l>
               <l>All the welthe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde with the iij. leues laye</l>
               <l>The fourth for woo fell and ſyghed full ſare</l>
               <l>With truth of the worlde was with the true maye</l>
               <l>¶ Thoughe his ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hede was dede his myght was the more</l>
               <l>On his holy handy werkes his herte was aye</l>
               <l>The ſoule with the god hede to hell dyde fare</l>
               <l>The body and the man hede dyd byde the iij. daye</l>
               <l>full yare</l>
               <l>¶ All that he with his handes had wrought</l>
               <l>And ſayth with his blode bought </l>
               <l>Tyll they were out of bale brought</l>
               <l>Hym longed full ſare</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="20">
               <l>¶ Than ſayd ſory ſathanas his ſolowe was ſadde</l>
               <l>For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyght of the ſelcuth he was nothynge fayne</l>
               <l>He ſayd to vs cometh ſom bodworde I trowe it be bad</l>
               <l>What art thou with thy fayre face thꝰ dyd hym frayne</l>
               <l>¶ Kynge of Ioye is my name thy geſtes to gladde</l>
               <l>Let me in for theyr loue thou ſholde not layne</l>
               <l>He ſayd wende awaye with thy myght thou makeſt vs all made</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:9890:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>What ſholde thou do in this pythere is nothyng but payne</l>
               <l>¶ Whan they herde the kynge ſpake</l>
               <l>All theyr gates they dyd ſhyt faſt</l>
               <l>Sone the barres dyd breke</l>
               <l>And all the bandes braſte</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="21">
               <l>¶ For his holy handy werkes there harowed he hell</l>
               <l>All the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brought out of bale that euer had ben his</l>
               <l>Dauyd his derlynge made myrthe them amonge</l>
               <l>With an herpe in his hande he harped I wyſſe</l>
               <l>¶ All his retenue out coude he tell</l>
               <l>And of his grete mercy forgaue them theyr myſſe</l>
               <l>He ſayd I was ſolde for your ſake and ſuffred wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des wyde</l>
               <l>And all my good chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be brought vnto blyſſe</l>
               <l>on the roode</l>
               <l>¶ The ſothe is not to layne </l>
               <l>Whan they were brought out of payne</l>
               <l>To the blyſſed body agayne</l>
               <l>The holy gooſt yode</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="22">
               <l>¶ The fourth lefe of the trueloue was folden for wo</l>
               <l>She was lefte mayde moder and wyfe</l>
               <l>The fyrſte lefe full of myght his wyll was ſo</l>
               <l>By the aſſente of the thyrde lefe was there no ſtryfe</l>
               <l>¶ They reyſed vp the ſeconde bytwene them two</l>
               <l>Thorowe myght of the godhede from dethe vnto lyfe</l>
               <l>He toke a croſſe in his hande and forthe he dyd go</l>
               <l>With his fleſſhe and his woundes fyfe</l>
               <l>he yode</l>
               <l>¶ When he was ryſen agayne </l>
               <l>He mette mary magdalayne</l>
               <l>It was no meruayle yf ſhe was fayne</l>
               <l>¶ He was her leche good</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="23">
               <l>¶ Forth wente mari magdalayne with myrth and with mode</l>
               <l>She tolde the tydynges to T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omas of ynde</l>
               <l>How cryſt was ryſen agayne that ſhed his hert blode</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:9890:6"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ words">
                     <desc>〈◊…〉</desc>
                  </gap>this Thomas thou ſhalte it true fynde</l>
               <l>¶ Then ſpake Thomas in ſtede there he ſtode</l>
               <l>Women be talkynge it cometh to them by kynde</l>
               <l>He wolde neuer byleue it tyll cryſte to hym yode</l>
               <l>And apered to the apoſtles ſo clerkes hath in mynde</l>
               <l>¶ He put his hande to his ſyde</l>
               <l>He bleſſed all that tyme</l>
               <l>That byleued on his woundes wyde</l>
               <l>And ſawe they neuer with eye</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Forthe wente the ſemly the ſoth for to ſaye</l>
               <l>To ſeke his dyſſyples that euer were true</l>
               <l>Sayth to our lady that he had loued ay</l>
               <l>All hole in his hurtes of hyde and of hewe</l>
               <l>¶ She was euer ſtable and ſtyll and fayled neuer faye</l>
               <l>The iiij. leues of troueloue they ſprynge euer newe</l>
               <l>Our lorde aſſended into heuen on holy thurſdaye</l>
               <l>Then folowed his moder with myrthes ynowe</l>
               <l>full euen</l>
               <l>¶ Before her ſone ſhe kneled downe </l>
               <l>With a good deuocyon</l>
               <l>On her hede he ſet a crowne</l>
               <l>And made her quene of heuen</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="25">
               <l>¶ The iiij. lefe of the trueloue bleſſed muſt ſhe be</l>
               <l>She may haue Ioye in her herte of her gentyll chylde</l>
               <l>On his faders ryght hande her ſone maye ſhe ſe</l>
               <l>And the holy ghoſt that to them can bylde</l>
               <l>¶ Now be they hole in one godhede &amp; perſones thre</l>
               <l>And ſhe is mayde of myght and moder full mylde</l>
               <l>Suche a nother trueloue growed neuer on tre</l>
               <l>Who ſo tryſteth on that trueloue ſhall not be gyled</l>
               <l>ſo hende</l>
               <l>¶ Wellis that wyght </l>
               <l>That maye beſure of the ſyght</l>
               <l>Where euer is daye and euer lyght</l>
               <l>And Ioye without ende</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="26">
               <pb facs="tcp:9890:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>¶ Thus hathe the fayre trueloue made vs all fre</l>
               <l>Our ſoules out of bondage &amp; bought vs on the rode</l>
               <l>He commaunded vs to kepe and gaue pauſte</l>
               <l>Our ſoules out of ſynne for ony worldes good</l>
               <l>¶ Moche ſorow wolde we haue &amp; we our ſoules myȝt ſe</l>
               <l>When they be ſonken in ſynne as ryſſhe in a flode</l>
               <l>Then abyde we in bondage in bale for to be</l>
               <l>He that vs boughte with his holy herte blode</l>
               <l>to haue blyſſe</l>
               <l>¶ He bad axe mercy whan we maye</l>
               <l>And byd our lady for vs pray </l>
               <l>Or we be cloſed in claye</l>
               <l>Or elles of our myrthe ſhall we myſſe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="27">
               <l>¶ Bleſſyd be the trueloue ſo meke and ſo mylde</l>
               <l>Sure and ſtedfaſt and ſtable in faye</l>
               <l>Whan we haue wrathed iij. with our werkes wylde</l>
               <l>The fourth lefe is gracyous and good vs to helpe aye</l>
               <l>¶ Then kneleth ſhe downe before her dere chylde</l>
               <l>Sore wepynge for our ſake with her eyes graye</l>
               <l>She is euer full of grace alas we were begyled</l>
               <l>She wynneth with her wepynge many fayre praye</l>
               <l>for to kepe</l>
               <l>¶ Syth ſhe is welthe of our wele </l>
               <l>And all our care wolde kele</l>
               <l>Alas why make ye her to knele</l>
               <l>And for our werkes wepe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="28">
               <l>¶ There is none in this worlde ſo doughty nor ſo dere</l>
               <l>Kynge nor quene thoughe he were a crowne</l>
               <l>Nor no fayre ladyes of coloures ſo clere</l>
               <l>Whan dredfull dethe cometh it draweth all downe</l>
               <l>¶ Yet lyſt vs neuer leue it for preſte nor for fryer</l>
               <l>Tyll we fele we fall with ſwelte and with ſwowne</l>
               <l>Whan the bare body is broughte on bere</l>
               <l>Than fayleth all felawſhyp in felde and in towne</l>
               <l>¶ In a clothe be we knyt</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:9890:7"/>
               <l>Syth put in a pyt</l>
               <l>and erth vpon vs done</l>
               <l>Of all the worlde be we quyt</l>
               <l>Forgoten be we ſoone</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="29">
               <l>¶ For the caytyf corſe there is but lytell care</l>
               <l>&amp; we were ſure of our ſoules where they ſholde dwell</l>
               <l>But nowe is nowe in this worlde ſo wyſe his of lare</l>
               <l>Nor no clerke in comynge that therof can tell</l>
               <l>¶ How ferre and how fele our ſoules muſt fare</l>
               <l>Hardwayes is to heuen and haſty to hell</l>
               <l>In purgatory is grete payne who ſo cometh there</l>
               <l>Of moche wo ſhall they wyt that therin ſhall dwell</l>
               <l>ſo longe</l>
               <l>¶ What ſo euer we do here we fare </l>
               <l>Before vs ſhall we fynde there</l>
               <l>We maye be ſure of no more</l>
               <l>When paynes be full ſtronge</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="30">
               <l>¶ When grete fyers grym be made in our gate</l>
               <l>Then is there no gloſynge but it muſt we glyde</l>
               <l>When we be put in the payne ſo harde and ſo hote</l>
               <l>We ſeke after ſocoure on euery ſyde</l>
               <l>¶ We crye after kynne folke they come to vs to late</l>
               <l>Then he haue felte the fyer fayſed is our pryde</l>
               <l>Then of all our ſorowe no ſertayne we wate</l>
               <l>But truſte on the trueloue his mercy to abyde</l>
               <l>with drede</l>
               <l>¶ Now is tyme to begynne </l>
               <l>The trueloue to wynne</l>
               <l>That all our bales he maye blyn</l>
               <l>Whan he haue mooſt nede</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="31">
               <l>¶ Of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue lyued ones ſhall we knowe</l>
               <l>Whan we reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre our foule ſynnes ſore may we mone</l>
               <l>Whan the grete lorde aboue his bemes ſhall blowe</l>
               <l>And hye Iuſtyſe ſhall ſyt in his trone</l>
               <l>¶ And all the folke in the worlde ſhall ryſe on a rowe</l>
               <l>The quycke maye quake whan the dede ſhall vp ryſe</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:9890:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>We may lette for no ſhame our ſynnes to ſhowe</l>
               <l>There is no golde nor fee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may make our maynpryſe</l>
               <l>and kynne</l>
               <l>¶ For then is all our pryde gone </l>
               <l>Our robes and our ryche pane</l>
               <l>Saue a cryſome alone</l>
               <l>That we were cryſtened in</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="32">
               <l>¶ When we be called to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courte vs be houeth to here</l>
               <l>All ſhall be there ſene bonde men and free</l>
               <l>The ſoule and the body that longe hath ſen ſere</l>
               <l>Be houeth to be preſent at the ſemble</l>
               <l>¶ Euery ſoule ſhall be ſende to ſeke after his fere</l>
               <l>Whan cryſte well vs gather a grece lorde is he</l>
               <l>With our fleſſhe and our fell as we in worlde were</l>
               <l>Neuer more to ſonder after that daye be</l>
               <l>for to knowe</l>
               <l>¶ Our werkes be wryten and ſcorde</l>
               <l>In a rolle of recorde </l>
               <l>Before the grete lorde</l>
               <l>Full ſharply to ſhowe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="33">
               <l>¶ We muſt ſeke thyder in a ſymple tyer</l>
               <l>Tremblynge and quakynge as lefe on a tree</l>
               <l>Whan all the worlde is ſet with water and fyer</l>
               <l>There is no wre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che nor no wyll wyll wyſſhe vs to fle</l>
               <l>¶ When cryſte is greued he is a grym ſyer</l>
               <l>So many ſynfull wretches as he there ſhall ſee</l>
               <l>Then dare not his moder yf ſhe wolde deſyre</l>
               <l>Not ſpeke to her ſon ſo dredfull is he</l>
               <l>that daye</l>
               <l>¶ All to ſayntes in heuen </l>
               <l>They ſhall be ſtyll of theyr ſteuen</l>
               <l>They dare not a worde meuen</l>
               <l>For no man to praye</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="34">
               <l>¶ The werckes of mercy he wyll reken them ſeuen</l>
               <l>When I was thruſty how hardly haue ye me fedde</l>
               <l>When I was thruſty how hardly haue ye me gyuen</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:9890:8"/>
               <l>When I was naked how haue ye me cledde</l>
               <l>¶ When I was houſles harbowred ye me euen</l>
               <l>Or vyſyte me in ſyknes or ſought to my bedde</l>
               <l>Or comforted me in pryſon that worde I here meuen</l>
               <l>Or brought me to buryeng when deth hath me ſted</l>
               <l>they ſaye</l>
               <l>¶ Or lorde when ſawe we the </l>
               <l>Euer in ony ſuche degree</l>
               <l>He ſayd the leeſt in the name of me</l>
               <l>That thou myght praye</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="35">
               <l>¶ He wyll ſhewe vs his woundes blody and bare</l>
               <l>All he ſuffred for our ſake bytter and wyde</l>
               <l>Kynges and quenes before hym muſt fare</l>
               <l>Byſſhoppes and barons all muſt abyde</l>
               <l>¶ Erles and Emperoures none wyll he ſpare</l>
               <l>Preſtes nor prelates or perſones of pryde</l>
               <l>Iuſtyſe and Iuges of lawe and of lere</l>
               <l>That now be full ryall to rynne and to ryde</l>
               <l>in londe</l>
               <l>¶ Theyr dome ſhall they take there</l>
               <l>Ryght as they haue demed here</l>
               <l>When they were of myght more</l>
               <l>And domes had in hande</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="36">
               <l>¶ Ryche ladyes that hathe robes full yare</l>
               <l>Ryches and rubyes with gownes full wyde</l>
               <l>Bendes and myrroures and fyllettes full fayre</l>
               <l>Golde on theyr garlondes with perre and pryde</l>
               <l>¶ Kalle and kercheffes that coucheth on theyr heyre</l>
               <l>So ſharply and ſhynynge to ſhewe by theyr ſyde</l>
               <l>All that welthe is awaye and myrth moche more</l>
               <l>But yf we wyn the truloue vnglad maye we glyde</l>
               <l>for ſorowe</l>
               <l>¶ Betyme is beſt to begyn </l>
               <l>Or were ſonken in ſynne</l>
               <l>For then is nother kyth nor kynne</l>
               <l>Fro bale may vs borowe</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:9890:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg n="37">
               <l>¶ By lordes and ladyes all I wyll not ſaye</l>
               <l>But ſome thynge by other folkes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I fynde full wele</l>
               <l>The galande gedlynge that kythis gentry</l>
               <l>With daynty damoyſelles no man may dele</l>
               <l>¶ They haue purfels and perles and heddes full hye</l>
               <l>Thoughe her corſe be the myddle of her kattell</l>
               <l>Yf men talke of her kynne awaye wyll ſhe wrye</l>
               <l>Her fader and moder fayre wolde ſhe hyll</l>
               <l>and tyde</l>
               <l>¶ When that daye ſhall begyn </l>
               <l>No man ſhall ſhame with theyr kynne</l>
               <l>All ſhall ſhame with theyr ſynne</l>
               <l>And with theyr foule pryde</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="38">
               <l>¶ The dome of the trueloue full ſore maye we drede</l>
               <l>For then is all the tyme paſt of mercy to craue</l>
               <l>When euery man is demed after his owne dede</l>
               <l>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may not our ſelfe ſterte &amp; ſende forthe our knaue</l>
               <l>¶ For he rekeneth by reaſon ſo clerkes can rede</l>
               <l>He ſetteth on his ryght ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules that he wyll ſaue</l>
               <l>The ſynfull wretches that maye not ſpede</l>
               <l>Shall ſtande on his lefte hande awaye for to haue</l>
               <l>for aye</l>
               <l>¶ Then wyll our lady wepe ſore</l>
               <l>For ſorowe that ſhe ſhall ſe there </l>
               <l>Whan ſhe maye helpe no more</l>
               <l>Grete mournynge ſhall be that daye</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="39">
               <l>¶ Now is tyme for to ſpeke for them that wyll ſpede</l>
               <l>And ſeke after ſocoure and foly to flee</l>
               <l>And not on domes daye whan we haue mooſt nede</l>
               <l>Now is moche mercy and then wyll none be</l>
               <l>¶ When our dere lady dare not for drede</l>
               <l>Speke to her dere ſone ſo dredfull is he</l>
               <l>How maye we axe mercy for our myſdede</l>
               <l>That wyll not folowe to it whan it is fre</l>
               <l>thore</l>
               <l>There is no waye but ij. </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:9890:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Wheder that we ſhall go </l>
               <l>To wele and to woo</l>
               <l>To dwell for euermore</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="40">
               <l>¶ Thus the bryght byrde taught the true maye</l>
               <l>And ſhe bleſſyd his body his bone and his blode</l>
               <l>To the fourthe lefe I rede that we praye</l>
               <l>That ſhe wolde our meſſage do with a mylde mode</l>
               <l>¶ And ſpeke for the loue before the laſt daye</l>
               <l>To the thyrde lefe gracyous and good</l>
               <l>The loue of the iiij. leues that we wynne maye</l>
               <l>That grace graunt grete god that dyed on the rod.</l>
               <l>walkynge</l>
               <l>¶ This I herde in a valaye </l>
               <l>As I wente on my waye </l>
               <l>In a mournynge of maye</l>
               <l>Whan medowes can ſprynge</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Enprented at London in Flete ſtrete at the ſygne of the ſonne / by wynkyn de worde.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Wynkyn de Worde</figDesc>
                  <head>Wynkyn de Worde</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9890:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
